{"tossups": [{"question": "This lake is named for a tribe whose members called themselves \u201cthe long tails.\u201d The Fenians crossed this body of water and feigned raids near its eastern end at the Welland Canal. This lake was the site of a battle in the War of 1812 during which Oliver Hazard Perry noted, \u201cWe have met the enemy and they are ours\u201d and led to the Americans securing Detroit. For 10 points, what Great Lake shares its name with a canal running from Buffalo to Albany?", "answer": "Lake <b><u>Erie</u> </b> [Ankit Aggarwal]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This king signed the Treaty of Aberconwy with Llywelyn the Last. Alongside Gilbert de Clare, this king commanded his father's forces at the Battle of Evesham [eve-shum], where he defeated Simon de Montfort to end the Second Barons' War. This king, who undertook a successful conquest of Wales, crushed the upstart William Wallace at the Battle of Falkirk. For 10 points, name this English king who succeeded Henry III and was known as \"The Hammer of the Scots\" and \u201cLongshanks\u201d.", "answer": "<b><u>Edward I</u></b> [accept <b><u>Edward Longshanks</u></b> until \u201cLongshanks\u201d is read and prompt thereafter]  [Chris Manners]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An artist from this country was arrested after depicting this country's revolution in the painting <em>The March of Humanity</em>. Several skeletons in graduation caps appear in \"Gods of the Modern World,\" a work one artist from this country painted at Dartmouth College. A purported depiction of Lenin in a painting by an artist from this country led Nelson Rockefeller to destroy it against its artist's wishes. For 10 points, name this native country of the painter of <em>Man at the</em>  <em>Crossroads,</em> Diego Rivera.", "answer": "<b><u>Mexico</u></b> [or the United <b><u>Mexican</u></b> States; or Estados Unidos <b><u>Mexicanos</u></b>] [Chris Man<u>ners]</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "It's not the UK, but a team from this country sponsored by Emirates lost eight straight races to lose the 2013 America\u2019s Cup. This country contests both the Bledisloe Cup and the Freedom Cup in a sport where they are represented by a team that uses a silver fern as an emblem and performs the <em>Kapa o Pango</em> and the <em>Ka Mate</em>. For 10 points, name this country whose rugby union team, the All Blacks, performs the <em>haka,</em> a ceremonial war dance of its indigenous Maori people.", "answer": "<b><u>New Zealand</u></b> [or <b><u>Aotearoa</u></b>]  [Patrick Lia<u>o]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This island was the location of the extremely successful Carlson\u2019s Patrol. Had Gunichi Mikawa not retreated prematurely, he could have destroyed American transports at this island after the Battle of Savo Island. American forces invaded this island due to the construction of an airfield on its Lunga Point; after its capture, that airfield was renamed Henderson Field. For 10 points, name this island in the Solomons, the site of the first Allied counter-offensive after the Battle of Midway in 1942.", "answer": "<b><u>Guadalcanal</u></b> [or <b><u>Isatabu</u></b>]  [Joe Nutter]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The breakup of Pannotia at the beginning of this period led to the formation of the  supercontinent Gondwana. After discovering many <em>lagerstatten</em> from this period in a certain country, Adam Sedgwick named it after the Latin name for Wales. This period was followed by the Ordovician, and it saw the first appearance of trilobites. It began approximately 540 million years ago. For 10 points, name this first period of the Paleozoic [pale-ee-oh-ZOH-ic] Era, which contained a namesake \u201cexplosion\u201d of biodiversity.", "answer": "<b><u>Cambrian</u></b> period [accept <b><u>Cambrian explosion</u></b>]  [Max Schin<u>dler]</u>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Earth Science"}, {"question": "This organization recently discussed the Doha Development Agenda in the context of improving the position of developing countries. This organization conducts periodic international  economic talks known as \u201crounds.\u201d The 1995 Marrakech Agreement created this organization to displace the GATT. In 1999, a conference hosted by this organization in Seattle was the subject of massive street protests. For 10 points, name this international organization that regulates the exchange of goods and services among nations.", "answer": "<b><u>World Trade</u></b> Organization [or the <b><u>WTO</u></b>]  [Ankit Agg<u>arwal]</u>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man had previously been an Orthodox Party candidate before he was arrested. This man was the leader of a group that used the <em>Granma</em> yacht. He gave the \u201cHistory will absolve me\u201d speech following his arrest after the failure of the assault of the 26th of July Movement on the Moncada barracks. After his return, he led guerrilla fighters in the Sierra Maestra. For 10 points, identify this man who overthrew Fulgencio [ful-HEN-see-oh] Batista to become leader of Cuba.", "answer": "<b><u>F</u></b>idel Alejandro <b><u>Castro</u></b> Ruz [prompt on <b><u>Castro</u></b>]  [Zihan Zhen<u>g</u>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Bernard of Saxe-Weimar led cavalry into French service during this war that included the Battle of Allerheim. The city of Magdeburg was sacked by General Tilly during this war, whose early \u201cDanish\u201d phase resulted from the disastrous folly of pro-Protestant King Christian IV. For 10 points, name this religious war in Germany that lasted from 1618 to 1648?", "answer": "<b><u>Thirty Years</u></b>' War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Coronation glyphs from this culture are found on Altar Q at the site of Copan. Religious traditions among these people based on the <em>k\u2019atun</em> cycle are recorded in folding books called  <em>chilam balaam</em>. This culture\u2019s most notable creation includes a \u201cLong Count\u201d system and is more accurate than a Gregorian counterpart. For 10 points, what Mesoamerican culture created a  calendar that predicted the world\u2019s doom in 2012?", "answer": "<b><u>Maya</u></b> [or <b><u>Mayan</u></b>s]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This sect has an understanding which allows member congregations to use the word \u201cGreater\u201d in naming themselves. In 1995, it formally apologized for its role in perpetuating slavery and racism. This sect began with a convention in Augusta. For 10 points, name this largest protestant denomination in the United States, named for its geographic origins.", "answer": "<b><u>Southern Baptist</u></b> Convention [or <b><u>Southern Baptist</u></b> Church; prompt on <b><u>Baptist</u></b>]  T<u>his Southern Bapti</u>st pastor and tele<u>vangelist founded</u> Liberty University i<u>n</u> Lynchburg, Virginia. ANSWER: Jerry Lamon <b><u>Falwell</u></b>, Sr. [Evan Adams]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man had the word \u201cFreude\u201d replaced with \u201cFreiheit\u201d while conducting a performance of  Beethoven\u2019s Ninth at the Brandenburg Gate in 1989. John F. Kennedy was the dedicatee of his <em>Kaddish</em> symphony. He collaborated with Jerome Robbins and Stephen Sondheim on a musical about warring Puerto Rican and Caucasian gangs based on <em>Romeo and Juliet</em>. For 10 points, name this Jewish composer of <em>West Side Story</em>.", "answer": "Leonard <b><u>Bernstein</u> </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A \"monkey-eating\" type of this animal is native to the Philippines. Deforestation in South America threatens the habitat of a large \"harpy\" type of this bird. The Holy Roman Empire used a double-headed one to represent the church and the state. A blue depiction of this kind of animal was used as the emblem of the National Recovery Administration. For 10 points, name this bird, whose \"bald\" type is an American national symbol.", "answer": "<b><u>eagle</u></b>s [prompt on <b><u>bird</u></b> until mentioned]", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "As governor, this man authorized the invasion of Illinois by George Rogers Clark. As a lawyer, he defended his home colony\u2019s Two Penny Act in the so-called \u201cParson\u2019s Cause.\u201d This man succeeded Lord Dunmore to become the first non-royal governor of Virginia, and said in  one speech \u201cIf this be treason, make the most of it.\u201d For 10 points, name this man who declared  \u201cgive me liberty or give me death!\u201d", "answer": "Patrick <b><u>Henry</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man succeeded William Marcy as Governor of New York, and this man was friends with political boss Thurlow Weed. This anti-slavery politician, who was wounded by Lewis Powell, tried to purchase the U.S. Virgin Islands before buying land from Russia. For 10 points name this  Secretary of State under Lincoln and Johnson who bought Alaska, his namesake \u201cfolly.\u201d", "answer": "William Henry <b><u>Seward</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Ivy Mike made use of this process, which is enabled by the Teller-Ulam design. Inertial confinement attempts to cause this reaction in a deuterium or tritium pellet. A Japanese fishing boat\u2019s crew were affected by the <em>Castle Bravo</em> test of a weapon relying on this process. For 10 points, identify this joining together of atomic nuclei, used to power a hydrogen bomb.", "answer": "nuclear <b><u>fusion</u></b> [do not accept nuclear fission, prompt on general answers related to nuclear weapons]", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In the 1960s, several of this country\u2019s Christian political parties merged to form the</u></b>  <b><u>Christian Democratic Appeal. At the end of World War II, it suffered the \u201cHunger</u></b>  <b><u>Winter.\u201d Filmmaker Theo</u> (+) van Gogh was killed in this country, where Queen Beatrix <u>abdicated in 2013. This co</u>untry\u2019s former colonies include Suriname and (*)</b> Indonesia, and the United Nations\u2019 International Court of Justice is based in its city The Hague. For 10 points, name this country where Anne Frank hid in Amsterdam.", "answer": "Kingdom of the <b><u>Netherlands</u></b> [or <b><u>Holland</u></b> or Koninkrijk der <b><u>Nederland</u></b>en] [Saul Hankin]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Brahmagupta sometimes lends his name to this mathematician\u2019s identity writing a</u></b>  <b><u>product of sums of squares itself as a sum of squares. This man\u2019s most famous book was</u></b>  <b><u>among the first to use Arabic numerals.</u> (+) Binet\u2019s [bih-nays] formula gives values of a <u>sequence named after this man, and the</u> ratio between those values approximates the</b> (*) golden ratio. This mathematician developed his most famous result by considering the monthly reproduction of rabbits. For 10 points, identify this mathematician whose book <em>Liber Abaci</em> introduced a sequence beginning 1,1,2,3,5.", "answer": "Leonardo <b><u>Fibonacci</u></b> [or Leonardo <b><u>Bonacci</u></b>; or <b><u>Leonardo of Pisa</u></b>] [Max Schindler]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man received a warning from the Boston police for including a dominant seventh in</u></b> <b><u>an</u><u> arrangement of \u201cThe Star-Spangled Banner\u201d. W.H. Auden wrote a four-haiku text for</u></b> <b><u>this man\u2019s composition</u> </b><em><b><u>Elegy for</u></b></em> <b><u>(+)</u> </b><em><b><u>J.F.K.</u></b></em><b><u>, and he collaborated again with Auden on the</u> <u>William Hogarth-inspired opera</u></b> <em><b>The Rake\u2019s Progress</b></em><b>. One of his most famous works opens with a high (*)</b> bassoon solo and was accompanied by Sergei Diaghilev\u2019s [dee-AH-gi-levs] choreography for Vaslav Nijinsky [nih-JIN-ski]. For 10 points, name this composer who was present during the riot sparked by the 1913 premiere of his ballet <em>The Rite of Spring</em>.", "answer": "Igor <b><u>Stravinsky</u></b> [or Igor Fyodorovich <b><u>Stravinsky</u></b>]  [Rob Carson]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>Restitution for a Canadian equivalent of this policy was passed by the government of</u></b> <b><u>Br</u><u>ian Mulroney. Ansel Adams photographed people affected by this policy at</u><u> (+)</u> </b> <b><u>Manzanar. Places like Tule Lake were created by this policy\u2019s early advocates</u> on the State Personnel Board of (*)</b> California. Much of this policy was established through Executive Order 9066. <em>Ex parte Endo</em> concerned a man detained as part of this policy. For 10 points, name this policy that confined Americans of a certain Asian ethnicity during World War II.", "answer": "<b><u>Japanese</u></b>-American <b><u>Internment</u></b> during World War II [accept equivalents like <b><u>Japanese</u></b>-A<u>merican</u> <b><u>r</u><u>elocation</u></b>]  <u>[Mike Be</u>ntley]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>One of the signatories of this treaty</u> <u>would later be stationed in Constantinople. One side</u></b> <b><u>ar</u><u>gued that its terms mandated the re</u><u>nunciation of claims to the Bay Islands and the (+)</u></b> <b><u>Mosquito Coast. Many observers thought this treaty named for Lord Palmerston's minis</u>ter to Washington and Zachary Taylor's Secretary of State violated the (*</b>) Monroe Doctrine. Eventually abrogated by the 1901 Hay-Pauncefote Treaty, for 10 points, identify this 1850 treaty declaring that neither the US nor Britain would build a canal in Central America without mutual consent.", "answer": "<b><u>Clayton-Bulwer</u> </b>Treaty  [Zeke Berdi<u>chevsky]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One monarch with this name was betrayed by nobles under William Kirkcaldy after an</u></b> <b><u>ag</u><u>reement at Carberry Hill. That monarch of this name was accused of conspiring with th</u><u>e</u></b> <b><u>Earl of Bothwell to order the murder of Lord</u><u> (+) Darnley and of writing the Casket</u> <u>Letters. Another monarch with this name sup</u>pressed Wyatt\u2019s Rebellion after the </b> <b>announcement of (*)</b> her marriage to Philip of Spain and oversaw the execution of Thomas Cranmer. For 10 points, give the name shared by James I\u2019s mother and a Queen whose  persecution of Protestants gave rise to her nickname \u201cBloody\u201d.", "answer": "<b><u>Mary</u></b> [or <b><u>Mary</u></b>, Queen of Scots; or <b><u>Mary</u></b> I; or <b><u>Mary</u></b> Tudor; or Bloody <b><u>Mary</u></b>] [Chris Chie<u>go]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}